A Register to the Natalie Grant Wraga Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Natalie Grant Wraga Papers
1919-2004
2005C55
Hoover Institution Archives
31 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (12.8 linear feet)
The papers of the American Foreign Service officer and Sovietologist include writings, notes, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to the Soviet government, foreign policy, espionage and clandestine activities, and especially the use of disinformation as a tactic. Includes photocopies of United States Department of State dispatches relating to Soviet activities during the 1920s and 1930s. Includes a typescript book-length-study entitled "Window on Russia." Also includes some papers of Ryszard (Richard) Wraga, Sovietologist and husband of Natalie Wraga. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Wraga, Natalie Grant, 1901-2002.
Access
The collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biography Note
1901 February 24 Born as Natalie Konstantinovna Mark, Tallinn, Estonia
1920s Fled the Soviet Union. Became a U.S. citizen when she married Malcolm Grant (divorced shortly thereafter)
1923 Employed with the American Relief Administration
1928-1939 Worked for the American Legation in Riga, Latvia, as a translator and analyst
1950s Employed with the U.S. Department of State as a Sovietologist
1959 May 20 Married Ryszard Wraga, also known as Jerzy Antoni Niezbrzycki
Mid-1960s Moved to Menlo Park, California, and worked for the Hoover Institution, Stanford University
1981-1988 Volunteer, League of Women Voters
1983-1985 Volunteer, Project Hope
1985 Volunteer, Republican Women's Club of Loudoun County, Virginia
2002 November 12 Died, Lovettsville, Virginia
Scope and Content of Collection
Natalie Grant Wraga papers include correspondence, notes, writings, and printed matter relating to the Soviet Government, U.S. foreign policy, espionage and clandestine activities, and the use of disinformation as opposed to simple propaganda as a tactic.
The largest series, Speeches and Writings, includes her typescript, book-length study entitled "Window on Russia." Writing under the name Natalie Grant, she was also the author of several monographs and articles in intelligence journals. She was an authority on "The Trust," one of the most important Soviet deception operations, in which a phony opposition group in the 1920s tricked émigrés and domestic opponents of the new Soviet regime into exposing their plans and feeding false information to the West.
The Subject File contains material related to her own publications. This includes articles and notes about Bolsheviks, communism, disinformation, emigration, espionage, the GPU (Glavnoe Politicheskoe Upravlenie or Main Political Administration), Russian civil war, etc. It also includes photocopies of U.S. Department of State dispatches relating to Soviet activities during the 1920s and 1930s.
The Richard (Ryszard) Wraga File contains papers of Richard (Ryszard) Wraga, Sovietologist and husband of Natalie Wraga. The Hoover Institution Archives also holds a separate collection of his materials, the Ryszard Wraga papers. Additional papers of Richard Wraga are available at the Józef Pilsudski Institute of America in New York City.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 10 series: Biographical File, Richard Wraga File, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Soviet Delegations File, Writings by Others, Newspapers and Clippings, Photographs and Negatives, and Oversize Material.
Wraga, Ryszard.; Disinformation.; Espionage, Russian.; Intelligence service--Soviet Union.; Secret service--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.; United States. Dept. of State.
- Biographical File, 1923-2006 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Address books, driver's license, employment and other service records, marriage certificate, notebook, obituaries, passports and other travel documents, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address/phone books
    - undated (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Driver's license, Virginia, 1975 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Employment and other service records
    - American Relief Administration, 1923 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - League of Women Voters material, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 1: 6)
      Includes Natalie Wraga proposal for study of U.S. national security, typescript, undated
    - Project Hope drive regarding supplying the needs of the women and children of the displaced persons camps in El Salvador
      - Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 1: 7)
      - "Local Woman Organizes Assistance Effort for El Salvador's Refugees," Loudoun Times-Mirror, 1984 October 11 (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - Award of merit, Project Hope, (The People-to-People Health Foundation, Inc. of Washington, D.C., 1985 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Republican Women's Club of Loudoun County (Virginia) material, 1985 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - U.S. Department of State (Box 2)
      - General, 1939, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 1)
      - Contract, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      - Correspondence, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Marriage certificate, 1959 May 20 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Notebook, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Obituaries, 2002 November 12 (Box-folder 2: 6-7)
    Includes letters of condolence
  - One hundredth birthday celebration, 2001
    - Greeting cards. (Box-folder 2: 8)
      Includes photographs
    - "A Worldly and Wise Woman's 100 Years," Loudoun Times-Mirror, 2001 March 4 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Passports and travel documents
    - International certificate of vaccination or revaccination, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - France--Carte de Séjour de Résident Temporaire, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Russia--Passport, 1923 (Box-folder 2: 12)
      Includes also passports of her parents (Mark, Konstantin Nikolaevich and Natalia Petrovna).
    - United States
      - Special (issued by the Department of State)
        - 1926 (Box-folder 2: 13)
        - 1928 (Box-folder 2: 14)
        - 1933 (Box-folder 2: 15)
        - 1936 (Box-folder 2: 16)
        - 1941 (Box-folder 2: 17)
        - 1953 (Box-folder 2: 18)
        - 1957 (Box-folder 2: 19)
      - General
        - 1970-1975 (Box-folder 2: 20)
        - 1975-1980 (Box-folder 2: 21)
        - 1980-1985 (Box-folder 2: 22)
        - 1996-2006 (Box-folder 2: 23)
- Richard Wraga File, 1950-1969. (Box 3)
  Correspondence, excerpts, notes, bibliography, obituaries, resume, subject file, and writings of Natalie Wraga's husband, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence, 1962-1969
    - undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1965-1969 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Excerpts, notes, bibliography, undated (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
  - Obituaries, 1968
    - Letters of condolence (Box-folder 3: 7-8)
    - Newsletters (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Resume, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Subject file
    - Hoover Institution, Stanford University, California, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - Research Institute on the Sino-Soviet Bloc, Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts, 1964 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Writings
    - "Abramov,", undated (Box-folder 3: 13)
      Typescript. Includes clippings
    - "Mukhoedstvo i pan Zagleba,", undated (Box-folder 3: 14)
      Typescript
    - "Otkliki o Sovetskikh marshalakh, arkticheskom metode i vtorostepennykh detaliakh," Vozrozhdenie, No. X., 1950 July-August (Box-folder 3: 15)
      Printed copy
    - "The Ideological Foundations of Bolshevism and Later Modifications," paper presented at symposium – Forty Years of the Soviet Regime, circa 1957 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - "Antagonism and Contradictions,", 1960 April 6 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - "Margin Notes," translated from newspaper Russkaya Mysl, 1960 December (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - "Colonialism within the USSR," paper presented at the Fourth Annual Roundtable Conference of the Institute of Ethnic Studies, Georgetown University, Washington, D.C., 1961 April 21 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - "Integral Communism: A Program for Action (Analysis of the Eighty-One Party Statement)," Monograph Series No. 2, Research Institute on the Sino-Soviet Bloc, Washington, D.C., 1961 (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - Untitled, 1961 February 26 (Box-folder 3: 21)
- Correspondence, 1921-2003
  Personal correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - 1921-2001 (Box-folder 4: 1)
      Includes unidentified photographs and negatives
    - International booksellers (Box-folder 4: 2)
      - 1968-1970
      - 1971-1981 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Congressmen-Diplomats, 1967-2000 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Editors
      - General, 1964-1991 (Box-folder 4: 5)
      - Unpublished material, 1957-1994
    - Newspapers, journals, institutions
      - 1967-1971 (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - 1972-1977 (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - 1978-1997 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Research, 1968-1983 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Unidentified, 1949-1981 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Albertini, G., and B. Souvarine, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Andreyev, N., 1970-1971 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Barth, Walter, 1979, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Berlau, John, 1998 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Bernier, Jean, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Biddlecombe, G., 1965 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Borman A., 1970 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Btotherus, Tapani, 1970 (Box-folder 4: 20)
  - Brownell, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Browzin, B. S., 1971 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Burgina, Anna, 1970, 1974 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Butenko, Vasilii, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Cannon, Howard W., 1975 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Carter, Woodbury, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - Christensen, Benedicte, 1996 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Cline, Ray S., 1980 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Cousins, Norman, 1975 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Ciolkosz, Adam, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Dorsey B. R., 1975 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Dziak, Jack, 1978, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Efman, V., 1952 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Eisenhower, Julie Nixon, 1977 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Eltchaninoff, Cyrille, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Eudin, X. J., 1968-1971 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Farrell, Frank, 1991 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Fertow, Nicolas, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Fischer, Frances, 1977 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Fisher, Joseph L., 1975-1987 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Gershel'man, A. S., 1970 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Grant, Malcolm and Brigham, Marye, 1968-2003 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Grenata, Michael, 1970-1983 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Gufler, Bernard, 1972 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Harris, William R., 1968-1969 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Harrop, William C., 1975 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Henderson, Loy, 1963-1981 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Humbert, Nicholas, 1969 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - Johnson, A. B., 1967-1968 (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - Johnsson, Stephen H., 1967-1984 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - Julchin, Simon H., 1978 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Kennan, George, 1951 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Kerblay, B., 1965 (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - Kharitonoff-Schelkoff, Marie, 1952-1977 (Box-folder 5: 28)
  - Kirkpatrick, Jeane, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 29)
  - Klementjew, N., 1970-1979 (Box-folder 5: 30)
  - Larin, G. P., 1968-1974 (Box-folder 5: 31)
  - Leggett, George H.
    - 1968-1972 (Box-folder 5: 32)
    - 1973-1986 (Box-folder 5: 33)
  - Lewytzkyi, Borys, 1969 (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - McCormick, Donald, and Richard Deacon, 1970-1988 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - McGowan, Everett W., and Mary Winslow, 1964-1970 (Box-folder 5: 36)
  - McSweeney, John P., 1975 (Box-folder 5: 37)
  - Mackiewicz, Josef, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 38)
  - Magerovsky, L. F., 1968-1978 (Box-folder 5: 39)
  - Mason, Frank E., 1975 (Box-folder 5: 40)
  - Melgounoff, S. P.
    - Undated (Box-folder 5: 41)
    - 1967-1978 (Box-folder 5: 42)
  - Meyer, George, 1968-1975 (Box-folder 5: 43)
  - Niezbrzyski, Vaclav, 1977 (Box-folder 5: 44)
  - Packer, Earl L.
    - 1963-1975 (Box-folder 5: 45)
    - 1976-1984 (Box-folder 5: 46)
  - Parry, Albert, 1973 (Box-folder 5: 47)
  - Patten, David A., 1985 (Box-folder 5: 48)
  - Pilon, Juliana, 1985 (Box-folder 5: 49)
  - Piroschkow, Vera, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 5: 50)
  - Possony, Regina, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 51)
  - Potapov, Victor, undated (Box-folder 5: 52)
  - Rafalskii, Sergei, 1972 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Riazance, Nicholai, 1970 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Rocca, Raymond, 1974, 1991 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Roosevelt, Edith Kermit, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Savinkoff L., 1971 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Scherbatow, Alexis, 1977 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Senutovich, V., 1971 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Sharp, Al, 1994-2000 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Simonov, Konstantin, 1960 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Spencer, Norman and Rosemary, 1963-1986 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Sretschinsky, G., 1969-1974 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Stosius, George, 1975 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Sulc, Lawrence B., undated (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Tang, Peter S.H., 1960-1969 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - Tinkoff-Utechin, Marina, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Tonsor, Stephen J., 1969 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Turubarova, M., 1972 (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Wedemeyer, A. C., 1972-1973 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Wolf, Frank, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - Wolfe, Ella and Bertram D., 1957-1984
    - 1964-1967 (Box-folder 6: 20)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 6: 21)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 6: 22)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 6: 23)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 6: 24)
    - 1972-1973 (Box-folder 6: 25)
    - 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6: 26)
    - 1977-1989 (Box-folder 6: 27)
  - Woyciechowski, Serge, 1968-1979 (Box-folder 6: 28)
  - Woytuk, Richard, 1976 (Box-folder 6: 29)
  - Wraga, Richard
    - Undated (Box-folder 6: 30-34)
    - 1950 (Box-folder 6: 35)
    - 1951
      - January-February (Box-folder 6: 36)
      - March-May (Box-folder 6: 37)
      - June-August (Box-folder 6: 38)
      - September-December (Box-folder 6: 39)
    - 1952 (Box 7)
      - April-May (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - June-July (Box-folder 7: 2)
      - August-December (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - 1953 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - 1954 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - 1955
      - January-July (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - August (Box-folder 7: 7)
      - September (Box-folder 7: 8)
      - October-December (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 7: 10)
    - 1957
      - January-May (Box-folder 7: 11)
      - June-July (Box-folder 7: 12)
      - August (Box-folder 7: 13)
      - September-December (Box-folder 7: 14)
    - 1958
      - January-February (Box-folder 7: 15)
      - March-July (Box-folder 7: 16)
      - August-November (Box-folder 7: 17)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 7: 18)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 7: 19)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 7: 20)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 7: 21)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 7: 22)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 7: 23)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Wrangel, Peter, 1970 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- Subject File, 1918-2001
  Clippings, monographs, printed copies, newspapers, typescripts, pamphlets and books, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Bolsheviks, 1918-1966 (Box-folder 16: 7-9)
  - Center for Soviet-American Dialogue, 1987 (Box-folder 16: 10)
  - Citizens for Public Discussion, 1987 (Box-folder 16: 11)
  - Communism, 1944-1971 (Box-folder 16: 12)
  - Conferences, 1969-1995 (Box-folder 16: 13)
  - Congress of Russian Americans, 1976-1992 (Box-folder 16: 14)
  - Defectees, 1940-1958 (Box-folder 16: 15)
  - DGB-SPD (Inter-relationship between the Federation of German Labor Unions (DGB) and the Socialist Party of Germany (SPD)), undated (Box-folder 16: 16)
  - Disinformation, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 16: 17)
  - Early "plots,", 1931 (Box-folder 16: 18)
    Includes notes
  - Emigration (Russian)
    - General, 1923-1975 (Box-folder 16: 19)
    - Latin America, undated (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - Espionage, 1928-1961 (Box-folder 17: 2)
  - Forgers, circa 1930-1966 (Box-folder 17: 3-5)
    Includes bibliography
  - GPU (Glavnoe Politicheskoe Upravlenie - Main Political Administration), 1921-1979 (Box-folder 17: 6-8)
  - Henderson, Loy W., oral history interview, 1973 June 14 (Box-folder 17: 9)
  - Hoover Institution (project) (Box-folder 17: 10)
  - Intelligence organizations – structure (Soviet abroad), undated (Box-folder 17: 11)
  - Kennan Institute, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 17: 12)
  - NTS (Narodno-Trudovoi Soiuz – People's Labor Union), undated (Box-folder 17: 13)
  - Opperput, 1920-1927 (Box-folder 17: 14)
  - Perekrestenko, Vladimir M., 1965 (Box-folder 17: 15)
    Curriculum vita
  - Psychological war, undated (Box-folder 17: 16)
  - Reviews of public material - CD [counterintelligence data?] memos, 1920-1970
    Photocopies
    - Volume 1 (Box-folder 17: 17)
    - Volume 1 (Box-folder 18: 1-6)
    - Volume 2 (Box-folder 18: 7-10)
    - Volume 3 (Box-folder 18: 11)
    - Volume 3 (Box-folder 19: 1-4)
    - Volume 4 (Box-folder 19: 5-9)
    - Volume 5 (Box-folder 19: 10-12)
    - Volume 5 (Box-folder 20: 1-2)
    - Volume 6 (Box-folder 20: 3-8)
    - Volume 7 (Box-folder 20: 9-12)
    - Volume 7 (Box-folder 21: 1-3)
    - Volume 8 (Box-folder 21: 4-8)
    - Volume 9 (Box-folder 21: 9-11)
    - Volume 10 (Box-folder 21: 12-14)
    - Volume 10 (Box-folder 22: 1-5)
  - Russian civil war, 1966, undated (Box-folder 22: 6)
  - State of the World Forum - Website information, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 22: 7-10)
  - United States - Congress. Hearings on Soviet Union and communism, 1949-1974
    - 1949 (Box-folder 22: 11)
    - 1954 (Box-folder 22: 12)
    - 1955 (Box-folder 22: 13)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 22: 14)
    - 1958 (Box-folder 22: 15)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 22: 16)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 22: 17)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 22: 18)
  - United States - Congress. Hearings on Soviet Union and communism, 1954-1974 (Folder 23)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 23: 2)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 23: 3)
  - United States – Department of State
    - Annual Guide to Public Policy Experts, Heritage Foundation
      - 1983 (Box-folder 23: 4)
      - 1984 (Box-folder 23: 5)
      - 1990 (Box-folder 23: 6)
      - 1993-1994 (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - Diplomatic and Consular Officers, Retired
      - 1972 (Box-folder 23: 8)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 23: 9)
    - International Relations Dictionary, 1978 (Box-folder 23: 10)
    - Paris telephone directory, Embassy (France), 1955 (Box-folder 23: 11)
    - Records, 1919-1947 (Folder 24)
      Includes Division of Foreign Service Administration, Division of Eastern European Affairs, Division on Russian Affairs
      - 1919-1921 (Box-folder 24: 1)
      - 1923 (Box-folder 24: 2)
      - 1924-1925 (Box-folder 24: 3)
      - 1926-1928 (Box-folder 24: 4)
      - 1931 (Box-folder 24: 5)
      - 1932 (Box-folder 24: 6)
      - 1933-1938 (Box-folder 24: 7)
      - 1943-1947 (Box-folder 24: 8)
  - USSR – Foreign policy – Strategy and tactics, 1963 (Box-folder 24: 9-12)
    - Wolf, Bertram and Ella, 1957-2000
      Including letters regarding N.Volski (N. Valentinov)
      - 1957-1960 (Box-folder 24: 13)
      - 1962-1964 (Box-folder 24: 14)
      - 1965 (Box-folder 24: 15)
      - 1966-2000 (Box-folder 24: 16)
  - Women for an Educated Society, undated (Box-folder 24: 17)
  - Zionism, undated (Box-folder 24: 18)
  - Miscellany, 1957-2001 (Box-folder 24: 19)
- Speeches and Writings, 1960-2002
  Articles relating chiefly to Russian history, politics, and culture, and to anticommunist movements, arranged chronologically
  - Letters to newspaper editors
    - 1965-1975 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - 1976-1977 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Notes to "Masters" articles, rough drafts, clippings, bibliographies, undated (Box-folder 8: 6-12)
  - Notes to "Masters" articles, rough drafts, clippings, bibliographies, undated (Box-folder 9: 1-4)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box-folder 9: 5-6)
    Manuscript, typescript
  - Untitled article about Soviet leaders, undated (Box-folder 9: 7)
    Typescript. Includes background material
  - Untitled manuscript on disinformation, undated (Box-folder 9: 8-9)
  - "A Forgotten Holocaust,", undated (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - "Problems of Leninism," draft, undated (Box-folder 9: 11-15)
  - "Trotskiy,", undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - "Tukhachevskii,", undated (Box-folder 10: 2-3)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "The Value of a Forgery," monograph draft, undated (Box-folder 10: 4-5)
  - "Zakhvat iazyka" (The Capture of a Tongue), draft, undated (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Untitled, 1951 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - "Pochemu?", 1951 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - "Skazka o volshebnom ozere," LA RENAISSANCE, Paris, 1951 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Short stories (fiction), 1956-1957 (Box-folder 10: 10-13)
    Drafts, handwritings, typescripts, letters from publishers.
  - Untitled play, circa 1960-1970 (Box-folder 10: 14)
  - "Disinformation," Bear and Dragon, published by National Review, Inc., 1960 (Box-folder 10: 15)
  - "Communist Psychological Offensive Distortions in the Translation of Official Documents," Pamphlet Series No. 1, Research Institute on the Sino-Soviet Bloc, 1961 (Box-folder 10: 16)
  - "Soviet Diplomatic Maneuvers: An Episode in the History of the Far Eastern Republic," Monograph Series No. 15, Research Institute on the Sino-Soviet Bloc, 1962 (Box-folder 10: 17)
  - "A Thermidorian Amalgam," The Russian Review, Vol. 22. No. 3, July 1963 (Box-folder 10: 18)
  - "As Others See It," Recorder, Menlo Park, California, 1963 October 24 (Box-folder 10: 19)
  - "Questions Goals," Recorder, Menlo Park, California, 1963 November 7 (Box-folder 10: 20)
  - "Two Lines Give Reds Wider Hold," Palo Alto Times, Palo Alto, California, 1964 May 9 (Box-folder 10: 21)
  - "Controversial," Recorder, Menlo Park, California, 1964 May 20 (Box-folder 10: 22)
  - "Viet Nam 'Logic' Requires Study," Palo Alto Times, Palo Alto, California, 1964 June 6 (Box-folder 10: 23)
  - "'Extremist' Term Vague," Palo Alto Times, Palo Alto, California, 1964 July 23 (Box-folder 10: 24)
  - "A Very Harsh 'Phase' Indeed," Palo Alto Times, Palo Alto, California, 1964 September 22 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - "Dilemma: What Should We Do about Uniting Germany?" San Carlos Enquirer, San Carlos, California, 1965 January 20 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - "'Individual Enterprise' in USSR is Just an Old Tactic," San Carlos Enquirer, San Carlos, California, 1965 January 13 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - "'Individual Enterprise' in USSR is Just an Old Tactic," Recorder, Menlo Park, California, 1965 January 20 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - "Interpreting Soviet News," San Carlos Enquirer, San Carlos, California, 1965 January 20 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - "Reds Say Ho Started War," Palo Alto Times, Palo Alto, California, 1965 January 27 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - "No Mystery to De Gaulle: He's 'Unyielding Patriot'" Recorder, Menlo Park, California, 1965 February 3 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - "Polite Attitude Now Fad with Governments at War," San Carlos Enquirer, San Carlos, California, 1965 February 3 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - "Communist Nations Launching Another Anti-American Campaign,", 1965 February 10 (Box-folder 11: 9)